[Music]
thank you
hello and welcome everyone this is
active live stream number 51.2 it's
November 9th 2022.
welcome to the active inference
Institute
we're a participatory online Institute
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference this
is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us feedback so
we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
participating in different Institute
projects
all right well
we're in
active stream number 51.2 we're in our
third discussion on the paper canonical
neural networks perform active inference
from 2022
we had a DOT zero video with some
background and context and overview and
then last week in 51.1 we had a great
discussion went over many interesting
details of the paper and related topics
So today we're going to jump in
cover some empirical details some
implications connect some more dots
maybe look at some code
and thanks again to kuya for joining
these discussions
um I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and
thought a lot over the last week about
what this kind of neural network
pomdp synthesis or translation really
means
and just want to learn more about what
fundamentals or foundational
aspects of these different kinds of
models enable that synthesis or
translation
and then again what that means for areas
where one or the other kind of model is
already in use so thanks again for
joining and I'll pass it to you
now if you want to say hi or give any
other a second introduction
oh yeah
um
brain Science Institute Japan so
I look forward to discuss another
different aspect
oh this this work so yeah
well let's just remind ourselves of
the fundamental
parallel being made in the paper and
then we'll get to these two questions
about kind of the two directions that
things can go
one representation is in equation one
with loss function of a neural network
and the free energy on a pomdp and
that's also seen visually in figure one
with the neural network being drawn a
concordance against the variational base
of the action perception Loop so maybe
just let's begin by restating what is
this parallel
that is in equation one and figure one
and what how was it reached in this
paper
so
basically uh idea here is that so we
would react to characterize the Dynamics
and plasticity of canonical neural
network in terms of Bayesian inference
because arbitrary dynamics of neural
network is an interruptable in the sense
that we we don't know what is the
function underlying such a Dynamics and
what is the consequence of the cell
organization or plasticity
so lastly translate that Dynamics in
terms of Bayesian Universe we can assign
a
quantities in Beijing instruments for
any biological quantities so which
enables us to lend the experiability to
the neural network Dynamics architecture
so a data basic idea and what we have
done in this paper is that we consider a
biologically plausible cost function for
this particular
canonical neural network and show the
the equivalence between that cost
function and the variational free energy
and the particular partially observable
organization process model
so yeah
awesome so let's look at the parallel
between the cost function for neural
networks and the variational free energy
so one representation of that was in
figure three so maybe could you just
describe
what is the structure of the variational
free energy
expression and what is the structure of
the loss function
okay so there is a career parallel
between the functional
structure or those component in
variational free energy under component
in neural network cost function so let's
say the first time in F corresponds to
the yeah it corresponds to the
to the expectation about the hidden
State s is the hidden State posterior
maybe so that that part basically
indicates
uh the the free energy with respect to
the hidden State yeah and the second
part
that correspond to the free energy but
the the decision posterior so yeah there
are the indicate the Australia believe
about agent decision or action
and now uh
in terms of the correspondence between
the free energy and neural network
function here the first time in the
neural and to cost function corresponds
to middle layer neural activity
which has recurrent connection
and let's see sensory input from sensory
layer and then project the the output to
the output rear
and the second term correspond to Output
layer which receive signals from
middleware and send
the the feedback response to the
environment
so both of these
Expressions have the first term being
more like a cognitive perceptual Sensory
Learning term and the second term is
more like a control theoretic action
selection
and
how did you see this analogy or
concordance because it looks like a
zipper like everything is totally
lined up
well
well so so these these the figure this
this graph itself showed uh Korea uh
correspondence because so now we are
considering a particular form of uh on
DB in which each element of hideous
State takes either zero or one but there
are many states so it is expressed in a
form of
you know
uh factorization
so now we consider that in terms of the
the the essence of the posterior bold OS
upper part of voltage correspond to the
expectation about each element of is
taking one
and the lower part of the board s
corresponds to the the expectation about
s taking zero so it is a broker about
the expectation posterior expectation
and this is a nicely
correspond to
the the the block Vector shown in the
bottom of uh this figure uh it is a
vector of X and
bias uh sorry it is a vector of X and
bar X and here by X indicate 1 minus X
in the elementalized sense
so which is a exactly correspond to uh
brokeback or asked expectation
and these correspondence uh also
observed in the second uh
here logos correspond to log X
and
also
log a it correspond to the block Matrix
of
W log W here
W hot indicate the sigmoidal function of
w and its bar means y bomb minus
sigmoidal function of w
so actually
uh because we now consider uh
uh binary
hidden State and binary observation it's
likely to mapping like refill mapping
from hidden state to observation is
expressed as a block Matrix which is the
exactly correspond to a product Matrix
shown in the bottom of this figure
select like this for every
time we have the exact correspondence
between the upper expression the lower
expression
so that's why we can say that this is a
natural mapping from a neural network
formation to operational Visa
information
so if it speaks as a sort of identity
between those two different expression
so although one may be able to consider
another mapping from neural network to
base an inference this is a this is a
sort of uh just simpress mapping
so how would it look different if it
were
three states categorical distribution or
a continuous distribution what
aspects would change
uh thank you for
asking that so that's a
in some sense outside of this paper in
because only when we consider a binary
State binary hidden State uh that this
this analogy
is
established nicely otherwise
we need to consider some extension
so because
consider that each neuron would
engineering called the probability or
expectation
of some value taking one then the
probability or expectation of the
of taking zero
can be simply computed by Computing one
minus your activity so actually neural
activity which is the single dimensional
variable is sufficient to express the
expectation right but once we consider
the three three state
hidden State
programs so this doesn't work so we need
to consider at least two
variables but its relation to
the neural network expression is not
very clear
in general
that's very
interesting why it would be so
strong of a Concordance
in a binary case
but immediately unclear
for other distributions
generally for common DP expression we
consider the one hotel
expression right one hot Vector
expression
which means that we memorize
the value uh
in the sense that some summation will
variable to be one
maybe there is some you know substrate
that achieve that normalization but for
for socrastic type of neural network
like canonical neural network considered
in this paper uh what is the that neural
substrate
is not not very clear so that's why we
selected the binary case because it's
simple and have a
create analogy
so what does it mean for a artificial or
for a biological neuron
to have activity Dynamics
or plasticity
context
that
justifies it being described as playing
like a belief role in a Bayesian setting
higher firing means more belief higher
firing means lower belief like what does
it really mean to have a connection
between activity Dynamics and belief
States
I see so if you if you assign a mapping
a particular mapping here its meaning is
also determining in this case we assign
that neural activity
correspond to the posterior expectation
about an element of hidden Escape taking
one so once we Define this mapping then
uh high on your activity indicate the
higher probability of taking one
so neural activity is the probability
neural activity is on the x-axis
and the y-axis of the sigmoid function
is the probability of taking one
well
uh neural activity
encode the expectation
so near activity is a sigmoidal function
of something itself
so this is because once we see a fixed
point of uh neural activity equation
which is derived from this cost function
it has a form of sigmoidal function so x
equals Sigma with our function of
grammograph
so this this form is exactly correspond
to uh
Source Max operations software marks
function of uh something which is seen
in the solution the posterior
expectation that is
so that's what the neural activity
encodes and what is the Bayesian
interpretation uh or the update rules on
the plasticity
okay that's another
important point so uh
in terms of uh poster or parameters
so in the case of Beijing for us we
consider the update about the delicate
parameter of of a matrix and B Matrix
which is usually expressed by the small
uh case variable
[Music]
and its meaning
is that so
if we compute the partial derivative of
a
sorry partial derivative of f with
respect to small a then its solution
it's fixed Point solution looks like uh
um
outer product of Sr o which is also
known as hempian product because it has
an energy to uh update to depending on
the create a synaptic neuron activity
and post Dynamic neuron activity and uh
according to this this formal
equivalence we
revisit we can see again such a such
analogy in a formal sense here uh
if we compute the partial derivative of
a neural network cost function with
respect to W then we get a
then we we did we can formally derive
the hebia plasticity which is depends on
the activity of prayer and post-synaptic
uh active neural activity
okay
so having plasticity
often described as neurons that fire
together wired together
here you're discussing it in terms of a
matrix operation on the pomdp side
between
observables
and hidden States
so there's a hebian plasticity happening
between
the perceptual layer
and that the cognitive layer
right
so the the first half the
um of the neural network
is trained according to heavy and
plasticity rules that optimize the a
in terms of the perceptual and
learning-like relationship between
hidden states and observables
and then the second half of the neural
network
has a slightly different structure
it is
optimizing based upon
retroactive
re-analysis of consequences of action
according to the fictive causality
construction
[Music]
so uh actually uh in this figure B uh
upper layer correspond to environment
and the lower part correspond to agents
so this structure corresponds to figure
A's you know this correspond to a
simpler version of phone DB so for good
version of omdp its corresponding neural
network
is showing figure four of this paper
okay
amazing task here we go this is the
neural network architecture all right
so as you said uh there is a network uh
connection from sensory layer to uh
coordinating layer which is expressed by
W here and the recurrent connection
which correspond to State transition
Matrix is extra expressed by K Matrix
which is recurrent assignment request a
synaptic connectivity and as you say the
action generation
through retrospective uh
reward or risk evolution is done by
output trigger through the
synaptic connectivity expressed as the
in this figure
so V is the synaptic connectivity
between
cognitive states in the middle layer and
the action selection States in y
EP and so in that way V is exactly
analogous to W but why and and how does
gamma come into play only in this second
layer I mean why not have Gamma 1 in the
first layer gamma 2 and the second layer
uh generally speaking it is possible to
moderate plasticity in a factory here
uh using another modulator
gamma but for Simplicity we focus only
on the neural modulation in the output
area
analogy is that for example as you said
the first right here the compute more
perceptual uh
things so perception of an external
world and
instead
on the other hand uh middle so on
secondary which is a
mapping from
cognitive layer to actually uh
perform the
optimization of its own action so for
example in
in the story item in the brain action
selection is optimized by moderation
of dopamination input
so usually that socket receives signal
from uh code card neural circuit and
send signal to another uh
neural neuronal uh nucleus in
meet a brain but a point here is that a
neuron in steriatum encodes some
decision for example go
or no goal so such a decision is encoded
so now uh we consider analogy between
Pond DP
expression in the basic information and
the neural circuit uh in the brain uh
that
that optimize
actions will
some some sort of modulation by
the another Factor here that factor
corresponds to gamma
and Laura gamer
he have
a
so gamma has a variety of
function but we in this paper we focus
only on the modulation of plasticity
so here the heavy and plasticity is not
determined by
on the uh for a post relationship but
so three factors relationship in the
sense that the plasticity is updated by
the product of gamma and pray and
post-synaptic
activity so there are three times in one
process to do
this is why this gamma can modulate
plasticity
so how would a glial factor
look different computationally and where
in the brain have people identified
glial or other factors as relevant for
learning
yeah that's interesting point I I'm not
really sure about the the equation of
the Greer moderation of neural activity
or plasticity there are many discussion
and I I don't
I'm sorry I I don't know the exact
the form but
one possible
implementation
is similar to this this type of
neuromodulation so
it would be possible to
model some real modulation we are a
contribution of glial factor to
plasticity in the form of three Factor
learning Group which is a mathematically
speaking in this same as this type of
neuromodulation
here in table two we have another
set of correspondences
it's like a sideways figure three
right but a little bit more like a
dictionary
anything to add or any variables that we
haven't really mentioned
what about the firing thresholds because
these are
common parameters
in a neural model
however
we don't really hear about the
interpretation
of these constructs
within the variational base pomdp
yeah there is a interesting
story so
yeah that's a very interesting point so
uh when we first try to make made an
analogy between
neural network on the Home Depot
and program one one program is a
the law of threshold Factor because as
you said it is not observing uh only be
structure but there is a another factor
in pond DB which is uh
prior brief prior expectation about the
hidden state which is usually expressed
by D Matrix
and we but what we consider is the
relationship between D Matrix and the
firing threshold and
uh finally what we found is that
aspiring threshold is not equal to D
Matrix itself but uh it is a summation
of D Matrix under some function of uh
synaptic strings or
which is equal to uh
a matrix B Matrix in the form DP
formation in other words what we found
is that h reached which is a firing
solution in neural network architecture
it is actually a
debate it is actually and and you know
adaptive threshold which is not function
which is not a
fixed value but H is a function of w
sine that big strings is
and it changes depending on the Ws value
for example if W is too large then
from your activity can be unstable so h
a we have to reduce the activity
to make a neural activity State more
stable so so we can see an analogy of
homeostatic mechanism here
so like this uh if if we
and so if we uh
design H as the function of w and
a function of some another factor which
is a
which is or
perturbation time in this table then we
we could make a common analogy between
this H and some variable in Palm DB
formulation which is shown in the right
hand side of this table although
its value is not simple because it have
a three times three different terms so
all of them
uh contribute to make age or M
M yeah but anyway once we we Maps age so
once we establish a mapping between H
and uh this value then everything works
so the cost function in different
setting have a Omar correspondence
what are the H and the M firing
thresholds
so H corresponds to Middle rare uh RMS
version
um M indicate the output layer
threshold
which are different variables and
interestingly H corresponds to uh
posterior sorry prior expectation about
the Hideous State because it correspond
to cognitive layer and M correspond to
prior belief about its own action
because it is a
it is a bias in the action layer
yeah it's very interesting that
the perceptual
firing threshold h
only includes
prior beliefs on hidden States
beliefs about how observations map to
Hidden States a and beliefs about how
hidden States change Through Time B
so that's like pure passive inference
and then the firing thresholds for M
correspond to only
beliefs about preferences and beliefs
about actions or habits with c and e so
there's like a complete division of
labor
or partitioning functionally
between these structurally different
parts of the neural network
and structurally different and
functionally different parts of the
pomdp foreign
yet they're integrated
in Unified
loss functions or unified imperatives
[Music]
and so it's like there's extreme
separability
of perception and action
on both sides of the figure one divide
but also
they're integrated but they're separate
and that's what kind of Grants it the
best of both worlds
because if they were any more integrated
you couldn't really pull them apart
and if they were any less integrated
then the imperative the loss function or
the variational free energy would be ad
hoc and unprincipled
but there's kind of a middle ground
where they have a principled integration
but still a distinguishment
right
huh
this is caused by you know Network
structure defined
[Music]
or it is because it is of energy with
this because the you know uh structure
of Bayesian uh major network uh defined
in the home DB
model so both of them Define the
causality relationship between elements
or quantities and so it's
you know its substrate is
not important so it's relationship
causal leadership is crucial to to
determine the cost function or it's a
fixed point in this context so that's
why we can
see the data analogy
well
there's a few
technical points I think we can now go
into and then there will be some more
General points about applications and
intelligence
so first
um
the code availability statement awesome
to see that the Matlab scripts are
available
and also archived on zenodo so here is
the GitHub repo for reverse engineering
do you want to give any overview
descriptions of what people can expect
to see in this repo and also what about
using Matlab
why did you use Matlab what advantages
or limitations do you see in Matlab
so uh because this is a very simple
simulation so
it is so macrob is sufficient called the
wall uh script
and
so we also try some visualization uh
uh in the material see here uh
uh if you run the script then uh
you can see the the
process of an agent solving the maze
task
so what do they do in the Maze task
so here the aim of this agent
is uh to
to leech the
right hand side of this Maze and so
because this is a typical example of a
delayed modulation task that's why we
select the maze task
uh so to achieve this main task is it
required to make some ground to
be able to uh select a good decision
because without
you know planning you may encounter the
war and cannot go for the and you may
fail the maze but with planning it is
possible to see the path to reach the
right hand side of this space
[Music]
so does it know its X position
so
ah yeah uh it let's see a state from
neighboring 11 times 11 service so which
is shown in the bottom part yeah this
all correct or uh most yeah left figure
see in indicate the observation so 11
times 11 state
around the
agent position
okay now agent is on the right hand side
of the maze at the goal position and it
observes a neighboring state
well a few interesting things
here it's looking off the right end
yeah and it has this kind of periodic
belief
in the key distribution why is that
uh
I think it is because
[Music]
when the agent is in the middle point of
maze then uh
all or neighboring state is in the Maze
so there is a uh
during the past and there is a war
so this makes some periodicity
because
Maize is may have some structures and
actually it's have a periodic structure
and only at the goal position then uh
right hand side becomes
War
but it is not common in the in for this
agent so because this is because this
agent believe
shows such a periodic
uh you know you know patterns
yeah the streets are one wide and they
tend to be separated by one
so we see this periodicity what is um
the numbers in this middle bottom plot
and what is the checkerboard represent
yeah
uh here q s on QD correspond to uh
positive expectation about the state and
the decision so uh middle
indicate uh decision posterior here and
the decision here we characterized
decision as the sequence of a four four
step options so each action corresponds
to a movement to
uh light or left or up or down
and we consider a full step sequence of
that action which is expressed as D so
uh it has a
well four
how four
uh
possibility
256.
yeah
256. so this is a product on uh x y
coordinate
because you know uh in the middle panel
uh Middle Point correspond to the
current position of agent and with the
four step movement agent can go uh yeah
one or any any current position
and the color
brightness corresponds to the
expectation
about the alien decision
well this is very interesting if we just
were to think about you're you're in a
point and you can go up down left right
you have four moves
naively it sounds like well it should
look like a gaussian blur
most of those should cancel out and then
it should become rarer and rarer
monotonically but actually
if you start in the middle
um you can't end up on these white
squares
because it's like one two three and then
you have to leave
right
so it's kind of like horses in chess or
other pieces we're actually their
embodiment
like it's very unexpected that you can't
in four moves end up next to where you
began
all right when you can be so much
further
and then we see this kind of like
embodied inferential prior with Qs
that embodies
um regularity beliefs about the width of
the road and the separation of the roads
and then there's these like embodied
action
priors and real consequences that have
to do with
the structure of movement
so what it's doing it's thinking
about policies of length four there's
256 policies of length 4.
there's some degeneracy because there's
obviously not 256 squares here
so while only one policy is going to
take you up up up up up
down down down down down
other squares are reachable like the
Center Square
is probably the mode
because it can be reached
at least a handful of ways
and then at each time point it's
basically saying okay I know where my
X position is
and given my local 11 by 11 View
I'm trying to plan to go right
and then here through time in the
simulation here it starts at 30
something
it quickly figures out how to get to
about 40.
and then it's kind of going up and down
on 40. but it can't really break out
because all of these bottom four routes
are closed
it has a breakout and then very quickly
it hits another Plateau around 60.
all right
then it kind of has a very nice Breakout
and in just a few steps goes very far
so what is dopamine doing or how is
dopamine helping it
in the plateau than to break out of the
plateau
yes
so uh this agent uh learned these
particular maze structure uh by uh
through many criers
so before training it failed to reach
the goal but after training it achieved
such a such a nice behavior so to
achieve this the role of dopamine is
that we design a gamma function such
that if
the agent can move rightward with some
distance during some time limit then
risk becomes small so like say gamma
equals zero so no risk situation in that
sense in that case
this this agent update synaptic weights
through heavier plasticity
but if the agent failed to go rightward
uh with some distance
during a limited time frame the gamma
become large like 0.6
which is larger than the average 0.5
then
we
designed that drawing in such situation
antihabian plasticity occurred instead
of heavier plasticity so anti-interia
plasticity
indicates the works as the
disassociation between the current
state and current decisions because this
the current decision does work it's it's
not good decision so we try to make the
Aged forget that particular decision
rules through the modulation of heavy
and plasticity done by Dharma Factory so
this can be
a a narrow a narrow to the dopam magic
modulation heavier plasticity
so if the policy is resulting in the
expected outcome gamma stays at 0.5
the policy is as risky or consequential
as expected
and then the policy can either go better
than expected
which facilitates learning to support
that decision to be made more or the
outcome of the policy can be worse than
expected which disassociates previous
conceptions
to discourage that kind of behavior
a crucial point is that this Association
done with a different time frame in the
sense that we consider uh
multiplication of current risk and the
past decisions the average
over past two
present hebian product this makes an
association between past decision
sequence and the current risk which
enables to
optimize the decision to
minimize the future risk right it is
just a shift of time frame
so here risk is being used in
a formal sense similar to how it's used
in economics which is the associated
uncertainty of outcomes with respect to
a policy
where does danger come into play
like what if there was a
adversary in the maze
or something that was dangerous
how does this kind of model accommodate
or hunger
or different kinds of competitions
because right now it's basically just
trying to defuse right word with a bias
right
but how do different kind of um
situational elements
become integrated into the generative
model and generative process
okay
any of
those factors can be involved in a risk
factor a single risk factor so you you
can actually design and risk factor
because risk factor modulate uh moderate
generative model so that's why Agent try
to minimize the risk
uh
through through uh Beijing updating but
the risk itself uh is in some sense
outside of such a basier framework we so
we can design
arbitrary risk so it may involve some
danger up to any
any other Factor
and this simulation
it is
a pomdp
or it is a neural network and what
scripts might we look at to understand
the structure of the maze agents
okay uh it is basically
expressed using the quantity in ondp for
tractability but for example if you see
the
mdp
well this is amazing stuff
learning probably
okay uh there is a
variable Sim type
uh on the in the definition of yes
same type correspond to the type of
simulation so if it's one or two it
becomes uh DP or neural network
uh to my understanding
well
uh in this particular
example well we
use
the
let's say
oh
maybe it's not good examples the
difference is
I'm clearing the
uh
yeah well so no difference in this
script as well so maybe another example
uh
let's see
what is mdp init is initiating the
market decision process exactly it's
just determine the initial State uh of
the home dvd simulation
and the variation of b f e computer
variational free energy
or risk
mdp risk computer risk function so
yeah basically we use the neural network
[Music]
structure computation in this particular
setup
so when you click
uh maze dot m
then
in the line
line starting one
line 31 we determine that the Sim type
is two this corresponds to neural
network
uh architecture so
there is a very slight difference
between home DP architecture and neural
network architecture because uh assuming
neural network architecture correspond
to you know uh
considering
uh
[Music]
how
to configuring this well
let's say
so
okay uh well
if you if you choose the the pump DB the
architecture then
we sometimes use the gamma function to
compute the posterior expected of
expectation about the parameters
but in the neural networking
the gamma function does appear but it is
replaced with the logarithm of some
function
and asymmetrically speaking the
difference between the gamma function of
something and the logarith function of
something is a
asymptotically saying so that's why we
can transform Ponte P2 uh
neural network architecture away the
number of samples is sufficiently large
so which which form do you expect
prefers better or performs better under
small or large amounts of data
uh
uh well for a large amount of data jbox
uh in the same manner assembly saying
money or small
amount of samples
I'm not truly sure but the
it's deep it's correspond to assumption
about the posteriority distribution so
if you assume dealership distribution
then uh
your your resulting function functional
form is
something that use the you know tigama
function
in terms of visual difference probably
which is optimal
no problem
all right let's return to the earliest
questions from today
so
um
in your script which people can
reference there's basically a toggle
between having it in Sim type 1 or Sim
type 2.
corresponding to the pomdp and the
neural network
what about if there's a published neural
network or pomdp
how can we use this architecture
to create a translation
is there any difference in this kind of
like translating models in the wild
different than the full
Construction
of a special script that can
speak both languages
well in terms of script there are no
difference as
a symptomatic difference
right so so this they they works
in the same manner so only uh
translation of variable
is
so so so you can you can
you can see the
the the same source code in the two
different ways so if you see that this
is a neural network generation then it's
it it is translated as a neural network
or if you see that this is a common DP
then it's more TP
so for some neural networks being used
in an industrial setting
um how would we get from the neural
network to a pomdp
and where would where or how would that
representation be valuable
right
so
so when neural network
in the different architecture so you
know so the important point is that so
we we consider a particular form of
neural network which is called canonical
neural network
architecture so only when we
assume this class of neural network then
you can find the exact correspondence to
a particular home on DB otherwise you
need to establish another equivalence
between another form of neural network
architecture and some sort of
Bayesian model
this this may be expressed by phone DP
but maybe not
no sourced red forward to be expressed
as the conventional BP architecture
so what is it about the canonical neural
network architecture
that facilitates its translation into
the pomdp form
yeah first of all it assumes the
sigmoider of deviation function it is
nicely correspond to enthalpy down in
the from GP equation only evaluations
so that's why we
we can
create Korea marketing so yeah in other
words
simply speaking they they have the same
non-linearity that's why this
translation is very easy
so
with another non-linearity or on your
neural network equation then
we we need to find another type of
entropy equation or another type of
Prior distribution which is a very
non-trivial
how does one even go about
doing that research
well
well so if you if you want want to go
that direction then I think the first
step is to find the
prior wave which makes
a
which makes
so
find the priority and
find the equivalence between a
particular neural network architecture
and particular Bay General model
s
this
sigmoidal activation is interesting it
corresponds to
General patterns seen in psychophysics
right two objects that are the same way
you're going to have a 50 chance of
saying that one is heavier
and then initially the difference has
the most
um Returns on
that decision being made
accurately
yeah and then as it crosses some
thresholds
where it just is the Beyond a noticeable
difference
the decision becomes essentially
probabilistic like the firing curve
becomes saturated
the neuron is at the it has very low
belief about zero or very high belief
about zero or one flip that
um
so there there is a nice grounding of
that kind of a sigmoidal response curve
with respect to stimuli differences
and it has of course
tractable
analytical properties but it also just
happens to resp be a good response
summarizer
yeah you're right so uh sigmoidal
function is also known as a psychometric
function as you say uh we observe the
that
characteristic in many
psychological experiments and the
previous work also said that uh
uh even at the single neural level
neuronal level the same behavior
were observed which means that for each
neural activity we can
re observe the similar property which is
uh sometimes called as neurometric
function so which is a
which have the form of sigmometer
activation function
so it is nice you know uh
listen to to to
you know design neural network
architecture using a sigmoiler
function
all right let's
cover a few
um questions in the chat from Dave and
then in the end turn to some general
thoughts
okay this was when we were looking at
figure three
so you described these
[Music]
um
vectors or matrices what kind of Matrix
or vector did you describe them as
well block Matrix
Matrix
block
meaning what
okay uh broke Matrix or Brook Vector is
a vectile vector or Matrix of Matrix so
so imagine that
foreign
just
repeat the last piece
okay uh I'll stay so well uh block
Matrix means that so element of Matrix
is a matrix
so let the let's say two by two Matrix
like Matrix in the yeah
you point pointing
so this here
W1 hat is a matrix
and the w0 Hut is another Matrix
and combining four matrices we Define a
single block Matrix
all right
thank you
so
Dave then asks
the hosts of machine learning Street
Talk number 67
with Carl friston another
uh podcast where ferson has spoken
pressed Carl friston on why is it so
important that most of the values in a
generative model Matrix assume values of
exactly zero
why is it important that generative
model matrices are sparse
why uh
[Music]
support I I I I I'm not fully sure I
think there is some context before that
that point
I think on a particular situation then
yeah as you say the many elements in The
Matrix so gently model should be zero
but I'm not sure if it's a general
statement at all
what do you think about compressed
analyzes on sparse matrices
uh-huh
is that a useful technique or Direction
you can use that knowledge to
construct a model so you can you can use
that knowledge to make more accurate
inference so in that sense yeah in
general speaking such as option should
be useful
uh for example
yeah as you said it would be possible to
use some
parts per year
to to to restrict the value of parameter
like it is in in principles same as
assuming some uh everyone knows
to design the the distribution to design
the prior distribution which is the
mathematical speaking exactly same as
considering lasso regression
yes
so
we've explored a little bit how from a
canonical neural network to a particular
form of a pomdp
and gives us some
semantics and interpretability around
the Dynamics and plasticity of the
neural network
what do we gain
by taking a stated pomdp generative
model
and deriving
an analogous neural network
do we gain access to
efficient computation new software
packages different applications
well
if one use home DB and
Lance Gories so design efficient
Bayesian model
okay I think
your pong DB expression is sufficient so
you don't need
you don't need to
consider neural network architecture
probably because sufficient inference or
omdp
architecture on the Bayesian formulation
is designed to achieve the some sort of
mathematical optimal
inference and decision making right so
it itself is optimal
scheme but if you if one need to
consider
um link between
in our Bayesian inference and the
biological substrate then then this
mapping is crucial
so yeah
simply speaking uh we consider that we
assume that a brain performed Beijing
inference but its substrate is still
unclear so we need to link the Bayesian
quantity to particular biological
quantities so this mapping this
equivalence helped us to its translation
right so when you start from home DB
model then uh this translation
facilitates the
the process of finding its neural noun
substrate
so once you translate that to a basic
answer to a neural network quantities
then it it help us it facilitates the
experimental validation or application
to real data so
if it's it's modern is world it is a apt
for a particular uh neural network
neural Starkey architecture then
so
it should provide some prediction about
the architecture or dynamics of
the empirical data
right so first we start from Bayesian
model which is not necessary to be equal
to empirical data so maybe there is some
mapping but it's mapping is not
straightforward we may have much pre
multiple mappings but once you translate
uh Bayesian model to a particular neural
network architecture then
um mapping or relationship between
empirical data to such a particular
neural network model is straightforward
so it helps us to apply base to an
explanation of empirical data that's a
my
soul
so
is it fair to say that neural networks
have found wide recent application
because they facilitate statistical
learning in cases where the inference
problem has not been a priori
well-specified
one can just have a folder of images
and a list of labels
and just say
here's the data
run it through this architecture or this
architecture Explorer
and so with this concordance we gain new
interpretability into those settings
that kind of arose from ill-specified
inference problems
and then on the other hand for problems
that we already have well specified in
terms of a pomdp generative model of a
particular form
we gain the connection to actually
implement it
with empirical data and bring it into
relevant industrial settings
what systems or phenomena
are promising
to continue research on
the main example obviously is
a simple case
but are you continuing Research into
more advanced computational agents
robotic
animal
oh hello
yeah you you can you can one can design
uh more uh sophisticated uh agent uh
which performs some difficult tasks
based on on uh canonical Network neural
network
but there is some limitation career
limitation
on that direction right so yeah I I
should emphasize that across of
canonical neural network which
correspond to a particular upon DB is
much smaller than
uh General commodity framework
so there are some limitations a list of
limitations so if one's goal is designed
and sophisticated Beijing to perform
some tasks or control robot then uh One
Direction is just just forget the such
limitation and
seek the mathematical optimality right
and another direction is biological
probability so if one want to make some
agent which is particularly possible
then is correspondence is crucial
because it it tells us on
limitation the biological limitation uh
through uh the existence or no existence
of such a mapping between pump DPS
particular neural network and
architecture
so
yeah
so it would be useful to consider a
biological substrate to achieve
on difficult tasks
and that task would be related to high
yeah large dimensional image processing
image recognition or sound recognition
such a multi-modality can be involved or
decision can be
higher dimensional like we in the Maze
task we just consider the four
directional movement but it can be
extended to higher dimensionality like
um
and so on and so on so in Facebook
it is X
it can be extended in that direction
which
directions or questions
are you excited about or what areas of
studying the basis of biological and
computational intelligence are relevant
yes so
in terms of
the the importance of canonical Network
as you said it's it's bachu is a
vertical probability so it would be nice
that if we if we model some task which
is conducted by real animal and one they
already recorded some new active
different activity
then we design the task which is exactly
same as the task which is done by the
animal and then compare the simulated
agent and MP card data to discuss about
the similarity or difference between
the simulated agent and real animal that
that will be very interesting direction
of research
yeah and if there could be some
unexpected prediction or explanation
right in the computational agent that
would bolster the relationship
and then
um one other aspect is it would help
with the reproducibility
and the
documentation around Behavioral Studies
if the computational agents were
pre-registered
and someone said we've already done the
statistical power analyzes and we've
already explored with parameter sweeps
how many observations we need to make of
the two armed Bandit how many
observations of the three armed Bandit
should we do three mice a hundred times
or a hundred mice three times
those are
the total substance of Designing
research programs
and so having a formal representation
of Behavioral tasks that are being
studied will help us design behavioral
observations and experiments that aren't
simply ad hoc
[Music]
all right that's a interesting
application so so yeah these these
framework helps to design the
experimental setup itself
and what we often consider is the
prediction ability of this modern
canonical neural networks to predict
the stereo humanization or Dynamics
of the Dr neural network in the animal
during the learning process so in
principle it is possible to predict the
behavior after learning based only on uh
data in the
the initial stage because once we obtain
some empirical data then we can fit that
data to design a particular canonical
Network and canonical neural network uh
make some several organizations through
a minimization of a cost function which
is exactly same as the Bayesian belief
updating under a particular generative
model
which means that its Dynamics through
goes through the shortest path on the
free energy landscape which means that
we can
make some quantitative prediction about
the synaptic trajectory or
neural activity or any kind of
parameters so we demonstrated that using
in vitural neural network and uploaded
some preprint recently so at least
at the stage or at least at the level in
vitron network which is much simpler
than VR brain we could predict the
self-organization or uh
individual network using this canonical
Network architecture
and this support the probability of free
energy principle because
this canonical Network predicts the
several organizations through the
variational frequency minimization and
its solution its results
have a tight video type and correlation
between the correlation to actual cell
organization
that's very interesting experiment so
what
animal were the neurons from and what
was measured about these neurons
yes so uh that in vitro network
is obtained from blood embryo
uh we use a cortical
cells to make that individual Network
and task is a sort of causal inference
task which is which can be designed in a
homework Home Depot so imagine that so
we usually accumulate agents that
receive signals generated by ODB
genitive process and the process some
Bayesian task so we just replace that
Vision agent to uh clear individual
neural network so we stimulate neuron
with some signal which is made by some
hidden sources through likelihood
mapping
uh questions whether in Virtual Network
can aim for the hidden States
through some cell organization and they
can they they could import the hidden
causes
and they're yeah what does it look like
functionally when the neural network has
succeeded at inferring the hidden causes
yeah the the director of observation is
done by their response number of
response spikes to a particular
pattern no sensory input so again we can
see a clear correspondence between
neural activity level and posterior
belief about hidden state so here we see
uh earlier book response to uh an
electrical stimuli we see the response
from
10 to 13 millisec after each stimulation
and we compute the number of spikes
and that spikes changes their preference
in the sense that some neural
learn to preferentially respond to
Source one but not source 2.
so which is not a response to input
itself but it looks like a response to
particular source
so it is inference and which is a
empirical evidence that neural network
actually perform some sort of uh cause
our influence in another consistent with
traditional region inference and then we
compute another quantity in basic
inference in the real world car data we
showed that uh
is consistent with the prior belief
about hidden State and we also compute
the cyanobic weight statistically
through some connection strings
estimation method and show that that
plus that the
so as estimated synaptic strengths uh is
consistent with uh something encoding
posterior belief about parameters as
expected by the cell the theory
well
we looked at table two earlier right and
this is almost like the next step after
the theoretical Concordance
is all right well let's measure
the release of a neurotransmitter or the
empirical synaptic strength or the
firing threshold or all these different
features in different empirical
systems
um so what systems what experimental
systems does your group work in
uh
uh that
that in vitro system was made when I was
a PhD student so that is the experiment
we done in my my previous round and now
I move to the weekend Institute and we I
I'm a principal investigator of a salary
unit so now actually we don't
use any any experimental setup so so any
experimental by addition is down with
some collaboration so although I cannot
say a detail about that collaboration
but yeah we learned some incorporating
work about the validation of celery
using
[Music]
various animals yeah so we hope we can
show some interesting result following
result using animal data
very um interesting
yeah
well it speaks a lot to the
stage
that our field is in in certain ways
where
we've seen a lot of
Graphics that are suggestive
this paper and the building on the
previous 2020 paper
made a suggestive
possibility
much closer to
a analytically demonstrated
translation and then took the next step
incrementally into the in silica agent
and so it's only natural to then
explore different embodied
systems as well
[Music]
um
are there any other sections that you
wanted to like look at or highlight
or any other topics about the paper or
adjacencies or active inference
that you think are interesting to go
into
yeah
so okay yeah
about some limitation of these papers
which is not the directory discussed in
the papers so
for example well we focus on a discrete
State space model so we
avoid to assume some substrate that
encodes okay
the covariance
of the distribution so once you actually
import the EP then it is categorical
distribution so it is different from
assuming gaussian distribution is
characterized by me and variance so the
neural substrate of variance
is still unclear and we now try to
figure out that so this is One Direction
of limitation
and another limitation is that thanks to
a simple simple ODP structure uh in this
paper we don't care about the
you know optimization but generally it
is crucial to update parameters through
hierarchical hierarchical optimization
solution
back propagation like computation
although it is unclear whether bug
propagation itself occurs in the real
brain but we still have some
alternative that achieve such a
optimization and its neural substrates
to unclear and this paper does other
address that direction
hmm
another area I'm wondering about is like
where in neural structures
is the learning reflected where where is
the function and learning reflected
well sometimes it has to do with not
just structural tweaking
but the presence or absence of synopsis
so obviously this model does not expand
into synaptogenesis synaptic pruning let
alone neurogenesis and neuro
um apoptosis which we mentioned in the
previous discussion but um understanding
how these larger scale structural
changes
which are certainly important in
biological systems
become reflected in artificial neural
networks and then how that translates
all the way back to pomdp and then
whether we could go the other way what
kinds of pomdp structures
in their neural network realization
would have structural modification like
you can imagine a pomdp
that does structure learning but the
neural network doesn't have structural
change
or there's a pomdp that doesn't do
structural learning but it's me it's
manifested by a neural network that does
have a structural change element
so structure is doing something very
different in these two different
categories model and then also
um even within neural firing
which
is different amongst different species
and so on
there's different
aspects of what that firing is
that would have different implications
for the actual biological substrate of
cognition like the simple
connection is firing rate
to posterior belief
average firing rate no change in
posterior reduce the firing rate if the
posterior should be going down increase
it if it should be going up
or maybe there are neurons that have a
flipped valence but the same type of
relationship but there's another
firing patterns
like Spike time dependent plasticity
synchronization amongst different brain
regions
there's a lot of things that don't
change the rate
overall
that again from the biological systems
we know that those phenomena and
mechanism are important for different
cognitive processes right
so there will be many many
years of a fruitful relationship
um
I'm gonna
bring in this
picture that that Alexandra had taken
maybe we need a third
panel in figure one
[Music]
because these three systems moving
between them
is going to be the substance of
the field for a long time
and there's maybe other edges to build
but understanding how artificial neural
networks
intermediate
between the empirical measurements and
manipulations that we can make of real
neural systems and
the
interpretability
and factorizability of pomdps
it might be a bridge too far to go from
the pomdp to the neuron you could always
use this technique but it would be a
purely
descriptive statistic type approach
but it's so interesting that by
intermediating through
a Formal Connection
established in figure one I mean in
equation one but also shown here yeah
then we can kind of extend
the chain of explanation prediction
control design
all the way on through
and that just unlocks like an incredible
amount of Neuroscience that hasn't been
formalized
mathematically
and an incredible amount of generative
models
that have been specified for different
learning settings
sometimes even by analogy to biological
settings
but
the metaphor remains just a metaphor
until it's possible to intermediate
with this type of neural network
developments
yeah
that's a crucial point
hmm
it is easy to imagine that you know real
data earlier uh
phenomena can be modern using very
realistic neural model or gliar or the
synaptic model right
it is yeah we believe that it is
possible and then layer data sorry real
model is not not necessarily tractable
not necessarily useful because it is too
much complicated to analyze something so
we use some reduction usually
mathematically speaking which
corresponds to topological
transformation to make the model simple
and then we need to consider the
translation of that simplified neural
network model because neural network
model itself is not experimentary
explainable
which just represents some Dynamics and
its functional meaning is you know not
clear but thanks to the Bayesian
framework we have a very nice here even
framework to lens the experiment ability
and this translation this correspondence
helped us to link such a phenomena base
equation modeling and
functional base
equations
yeah one paper
um from 2017 that
was much discussed by some could a
neuroscientist understand a
microprocessor
and this uh group with Jonas and
courting
they had a simulation of a
microprocessor
from uh earlier
video game console I believe
and then using the analogy of like the
transistors and their connections as
neural firing and structural
connectivity
they were able to simulate
experimental settings input and action
and then make measurements from like
every neuron
including doing lesions and loss of
functions and so on and it turns out
that a lot of the techniques that are
used
to derive scientific explanation
from analogous data collected from a
biological system
those techniques which ostensibly should
be isolating functional explanations in
fact did not isolate effective
explanations you could have a deletion
over here that induces some statistical
change all the way over here and that
may or may not be a useful
clue towards the function of even
sub-circuits
and so I think that was a wake-up call
with respect to the interpretability of
um
simply
this connection
between the biological and the neural
network
this connection alone
is of limited applicability
um even when the neural network model
becomes so complex as to recapitulate
the biological phenomena
you're never under any guarantee that
you're going to recover interpretability
you may have just created an uh Atomic
level simulation
of the phenomena but of course a map
that is the same scale as the phenomena
isn't a map
it's just a copy that has no more
interpretability
um and it's almost like what what is now
extended
again as we kind of just summarize this
and think about how we move forward
is that connection can now be extended
into the space of interpretable causal
models
and the generalized Bayesian graphical
computational Frameworks
and all the heuristics that we can then
use like variational bays and all these
other methods
so it'd be interesting to look back at
different data sets of in vitro and in
Vivo and in silico
neural activation
especially if the task was of this
constrained set of pomdps
and it was already amenable because as
you brought up other
settings would require a little bit more
theory development
before we understand what pomdp family
would be applicable
cool well
do you have any final thoughts or
questions
wow
do you hop
I want to download the Matlab Scripts
and generate the figures
play around with a few of these
parameters
like I see that you can change how far
the entity can see
and then with these models I'm also
always curious about the computational
complexity
like if you extended the planning
Horizon from four to five or you dropped
it down to three
huh
what is the runtime consequences and
what is the performance consequences
and where might we be able to use
single or swarms
of really simple agents
maybe even making binary decisions
and Achieve high performance
and where do we really need to
move into these large combinatoric
spaces
in order to solve problems
and the kinds of complex planning
problems that we solve
whether it's planning our day or
planning our week
are those more like
true deep Horizon planning problems
with extensive consideration of
counterfactuals and calculation of
Alternatives or are those actually
composite
decisions that are made up of smaller
simpler sub-decisions
that we may or may not have flexibility
to restructure
so that a decision
a complex chess maneuver a sacrifice in
chess or another game
[Music]
it may be possible to model that as
a deep Horizon scan
or
a kind of intuitive heuristic
for inappropriate skilled entity
or or this particular two layer
structure there is a career limitation
about the you know
The Horizon oh the your search or search
because it doesn't use for the
prediction it use the positive approach
so it's a career limitation but still it
may have some
performance
right that actually I mean that provides
even another
um
way to look at planning
so the the two ways I was describing
planning as it's often described in the
pmdp literature is again is it a true
deep Horizon consideration or is it just
short-term heuristics or nested models
that are short
and I think that
um this paper
says maybe neither
maybe it's purely
the fictive causality on the past
that leads to the emergence of sentience
and maybe even
teleological planning-like Behavior
through the ongoing reconsideration of
the consequences of past action
but it's neither a short nor long term
planning challenge it's actually like a
memory and learning Challenge and no
planning occurs right
but he indirectly planning you know
priming element is involving C Matrix
right
planning as a phenomena
occurs and de-risking Through Time
occurs but they're um but it says
something quite interesting and deep
that that
phenotype or function
could be enacted by A system that
explicitly looks a long way ahead
explicitly looks a short way ahead or
moves forward and looks backwards only
all right which is what they sometimes
say about the past and the future
so that may be
a very biologically plausible
form of learning
and it's already intimately connected
with the Dynamics and the plasticity
in terms of an integrated loss function
so these are all
excellent directions to keep learning on
right
and uh also interested in the bars
guardian premedition of such a short
time or wrong time for the prediction
I'm planning and I hope
to find some
nice connectivity to such a
implementation
of Bayesian model and
implementation in real brain Network
cool and also I'm I'm always curious
about the invertebrate brain
as a ants researcher
and so many of the
micro architectures
as well as the regional architectures
that people discuss
are babelian Centric which makes sense
the mammalian cortical column and the
relationship with uh um dopaminergic
midbrain and the cortical regions and
the spinal reflex arc those are all
important
systems of Interest yet the micro and
mesoanatomy of the invertebrate nervous
system
is pretty distinct
so
our model should be able to describe
neural and cognitive systems
of course across invertebrates and
vertebrates
so I look forward to also seeing like
what those models of the invertebrate
nervous system and
Collective Behavior
where you could have some type of
backwards looking
risk
inference
of the Swarm
um who knows who knows
well
we really appreciate the time that you
took for these discussions I think they
are immensely important and we wish you
the best of luck in these continued
directions
okay that's it thank you
thank you very much see you next time
bye
by